# **Balveer Singh**



balveersinghyt@gmail.com



linkedin.com/in/balveersinghyt



7973861409



https://www.balveersingh.in

# Summary

I'm a Computer Science Engineer interested in Software Development. I also love to build mechatronics-robotics projects and worked on 20+ projects during under graduation & taught the basics of programming, electronics, sensors, etc. to the juniors while working as a Lab Coordinator in IoT & Mech-Finix Lab.

I have one year of experience working under Prof. Ganesh Ramakrishnan as a Software Development Intern at IIT Bombay. I worked on Django-Python, server-side deployment & recruitment.

I'm a keen learner & always look forward to grabbing new opportunities.

# **Experience**



# Software Development Intern

Indian Institute of Technology, Bombay

Aug 2021 - Jul 2022 (1 year)

I did this internship under Prof. Ganesh Ramakrishnan on Akshar Anveshini & Udaan project. These projects are about the digitization & translation of Sanskrit books into different languages, so that we can preserve the heritage of Indian culture.

1. Worked on Project Manager User Interface(PMUI), Udaan Translation Tool Interface, OCR Tool Interface

for Indian Languages.

- 2. worked on the initial development of Web Based Tool Interface
- 3. Deployment on Jio, AICTE's VM using NGINX, Gunicorn web servers
- 4. Also worked as a recruiter for hiring new interns & interviewed 30+ candidates

More about the project:

Akshar Anveshini: https://www.cse.iitb.ac.in/~ocr/#akshar-anveshini

UDAAN-Project: https://www.udaanproject.org/

PMUI: https://pepmiitb.jio.com/

OCR Tool: https://pepmiitb.jio.com/ocr-interface/

Udaan Translation Tool: https://pepmiitb.jio.com/udaan/



#### Student Teacher

Baba Banda Singh Bahadur Engineering College

Jan 2021 - Apr 2021 (4 months)

During my final year of engineering, I got an opportunity to manage & set up the IoT Lab in the Department of Computer Science & Engineering. I used to teach the basics of the Internet of Things to my Juniors. After opening the lab 25 students enrolled in IoT Course. And at the end of March, we made 7 projects which made a huge contribution during the NAAC inspections.



### Co-Founder

Mech-Finix Labs

Feb 2020 - Apr 2021 (1 year 3 months)

We set up an innovation lab to encourage youngsters towards technical, non-technical & practical skills. The idea behind this lab is to give students a platform where they can make projects related to robotics, the Internet of Things, etc. Aside from that they can also teach their juniors & can get practical experience. The speciality of this lab is that it is running 24\*7 on college campus & managed by the students.

# Training in Raspberry Pi with Python Course

NATIONAL INSTITUTE OF ELECTRONICS & INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY (NIELIT)

Jun 2019 - Aug 2019 (3 months)

During my joint training with IIT & NIELIT Ropar, I enrolled in the Raspberry Pi course. In the duration of two months, I have learned the basics of Python, Web-Development & Introduction to Raspberry Pi.

I also got certification from CISCO Networking Acadamy in Python Essentials, Fundamental of Linux & Introduction to IoT courses.

After doing these courses I created one project there that was Face Recognition Attendance System. While creating this project I have learned a lot about the front end & backend implementation. Our goal was to make use of Raspberry Pi in such a way that we can use it as fog computing to put facerecognized data on the cloud.

# **Education**



#### CHANDIGARH UNIVERSITY

Master of Engineering - MEng, Artificial Intelligence & Machine Learning 2022 - 2024



### Baba Banda Singh Bahadur Engineering College

BTech - Bachelor of Technology, Computer Science Aug 2017 - Aug 2021

#### **Licenses & Certifications**



Certificate for Completion Of Linux Training - Spoken Tutorial

1932079ZPI



Certificate for Completion of Cpp Training - Spoken Tutorial

19320790D5

# NDG Linux Unhatched Course

- Programming Essentials in Python Cisco Networking Academy https://drive.google.com/file/d/19mBCh\_zSStu5VXWyyRI\_f2Bw-jQ8BmJg/view?usp=share
- loT Fundamental: Connecting Things Cisco Networking Academy
- Certificate for Completion of Java Training Spoken Tutorial 193207941
- Certificate of Appreciation Entrepreneurship Cell, IIT Kharagpur https://drive.google.com/file/d/1FvEJPWDnkPd-1g5Uotk1DJN-6YoEVvuc/view?usp=share
- Training Completion NATIONAL INSTITUTE OF ELECTRONICS & INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY (NIELIT)
  20015

## **Skills**

Nginx • gunicorn • REST APIs • Flask • Celery • User Interface Design • Python (Programming Language) • Back-End Web Development • Internet of Things (IoT) • Web Development